Guide to the Jacques Barzun's Collection of Hector Berlioz Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Subseries I.3: Copies
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Strakosch, Maurice, [Paris], n.d., (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Suat, [Camille], [Paris], Apr. 20, 1855, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Taylor, Mr., [Paris], Mar. 4, n.y., (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Thalberg, Sigismond, London, Paris, [1958], (4 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 78 - 81)
      [Originals in AA136]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Vatout, A. M., [Paris], Apr. 3, 1840, (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy), ) (Box 4, Folder 82)
      [Original in Archives Nationales, Paris]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Vernet, Horace, [Paris], Jul. 11, 1856, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Viardot, Pauline, Plombieres; [Paris], 1856 - 1860, (3 a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.; typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 84 - 86)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Vicaire, Gabriel, Paris, May 13, 1854, (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: de Villemessant, Auguste Cartier, [Paris], Jan. 5, 1845, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Vivier, Eugene Leon, [Paris], [Jul. 28, 1859], (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Wagner, Richard, [Paris], May 20, 1860, (a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy), ) (Box 4, Folder 90)
      [From: Bayreuther Blatter, 1905, 285-6.]
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
  Arranged alphabetically by title. Oversized materials stored in flat box (Box 48).
  - Subseries II.1: Originals
    - McNutt, Richard, Rare Book Dealer Collection list, Tunbridge Wells, England, n.d., (6 p. t.ms., ) (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Hector Berlioz Au Bord d'une Riviere, [Paris?], n.d., (1 p. a. ms., ) (Box 4, Folder 92)
      [Unpublished song, ms. notes on modal writing on verso]
    - Hector Berlioz Beatrice et Benedict, c. 1858, (64 p. ms., ) (Box 4, Folder 93)
      [Libretto in hand of copyist; corrections in hand of Berlioz]
    - Berlioz, Hector Benvenuto Cellini: Piano-vocal Score, act 3., n.d., (207p. ms., ) (Box 48, Folder 1)
      [Oversized material in flat box.]
    - Hector Berlioz La Captive: Orientale de Victor Hugo, musique de H. Berlioz, Subiaco, February 1872, (1 p. a.ms.s, ) (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Berlioz, Hector Le Chant Des Bretons, n.d., (39p. Printed score, signed by author, ) (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Berlioz, Hector L'enfance du Christ, pt. 1, 1854, (107p. ms., ) (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Hector Berlioz Nocturne, Paris, n.d., (4 p. a.ms., ) (Box 4, Folder 95)
      [Unpublished song for two soprani with guitar accompaniment]
    - Hector Berlioz Notes, 1862, (2 p. a.ms., ) (Box 4, Folder 96)
      [Notes of anticipated income and expenditures and agenda of projects for 1862]
    - Hector Berlioz Les Troyens - Draft libretto of the Prologue to Act III, Paris, 1863, (5 p. a.ms., ) (Box 4, Folder 97)
      [Draft libretto of the Prologue to Act III]
    - Hector Berlioz Personal accounts, Paris, January to August 1859, (16 p. a.d., ) (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Hector Berlioz Romeo et Juliette, 1839, (281 p. a. ms., ) (Box 4, Folder 99)
      [Symphonie avec chorus et solos de chant. Piano vocal score in the hand of a copyist, with autograph corrections by Berlioz]
    - Berlioz, Hector Les Troyens (La Prise de Troie, [Paris], ca. 1862, (8p. copyists ms. with ms. corrections, ) (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II.2: Copies
    Photostats and typescripts of Berlioz manuscripts in other collections and institutions.
    - Berlioz, Hector Page from memoirs, n.p., n.d., (1p. a. ms. (Photostat), ) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Berlioz, Hector Receipt, Stuttgart, Jan. 30, 1842, (1p. a. d. (Photostat), ) (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Berlioz, Hector Poem, Hartzburg, Oct. 28, 1953, (1p. a. ms. s. (Photostat), ) (Box 5, Folder 3)
      [Original at Yale University Goetheana Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector Note, Weimar, Feb. 26, 1855, (1p. a. ms. s. (Photostat), ) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Berlioz, Hector [Notes and corrections for his biographical sketch in the Le Dictionnaire Vapereau, 2nd ed.], n.p., [1856], (2p a.ms. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series III: Materials Commemorating Berlioz
  This series contains cataloged early (1880 - 1922) writings and images commemorating Berlioz from the collection of Jacques Barzu. Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Baillet, Gaston La Vie d'un Grand Artiste, [Grenoble], Mar. 21, 1905, (38p. ms. (mimeo)) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cortaillod Le Vieux Montmarte Societe d'Histoire et d'Archeologie 25th anniversary, Montmarte, Jun. 11, 1911, (4p. printed invitation and program) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Dettmer, Roger Copies of reviews from the N.Y Herald Tribune, New York, (4 t.ms.) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Farrington, Conor The Tribunal The Tribunal - radio play, 9 September 1960, (51p. t. ms.) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Pasquet, Adolphe Text of a circular pertaining to a bust of Berlioz, [Grenoble], Apr. 17, 1903, (1p. ms. (photostat)) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Scholz, Hans Aus dem Leben von Hector Berlioz, (10p. t. ms., ) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Scholz, Hans Berlioz in Schrifttum und Erlebnis, (10p. t. ms., ) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Shaw, George Bernard A Reminiscece of Hector Berlioz, London, 20 February 1880, (22p. a.ms.s. ) (Box 5, Folder 13)
    [copy made from original in British Museum. I`ncluded is a typescript critique of the piece intended for Jacques [Barzun] author unknown]
  - Tibbets pencil and wash drawing of Berlioz ca. 1845, n.p., Mar. 10, 1905, (1 35.5 x 25.5 cm, Signed) (Box 5, Folder 14)
    [thought to be a cover design for a book]
  - Zuth, Joseph Die Gitarre des Hektor Berlioz, Apr. 01, 1922, (30p. t.ms.) (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Arranged Correspondence
  - Subseries IV.1: Letters and essays by Tom S. Wotton
    Arrranged chronologically.
    - [Wotton, Tom S.] To: various people, London, Bath, 16 November 1900 - 27 Feb. 1901, (14 t.l. (copies), ) (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - [Wotton, Tom S.] To: various people, London, Bath, 27 Feb. 1901 - 1 Jun. 1901, (19 t.l. copies, ) (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - [Wotton, Tom S.] To: various people, London, Bath, 1 Jun. 1901 - 7 Nov. 1901, (34 t.l. copies, ) (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - [Wotton, Tom S.] To: various people, London, Bath, 8 Nov. 1901- 11 Feb. 1902, (31 t.l. copies, ) (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - [Wotton, Tom S.] To: various people, London, Bath, 12 Feb. 1902 - 28 May 1902, (28 t.l. copies, ) (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Wotton, Tom S. Paris, 4 Dec. 1905 - 1 Dec. 1905, (2 t.d.s. (Receipt and memo), ) (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - [Wotton, Tom S.] To: Joseph Baggers, London, 9 Sep. 1912 - 20 Sep. 1912, (3 t.l. (copies), ) (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - [Wotton, Tom S.] To: Mssrs. G. Ricordi and Co., London, Dec. 15, 1913, (2p. t.l. (carbon), ) (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Wotton, Tom S. To: Monsieur le Bibliothecaire, La Bibliotheque National, Paris, Hastings, January 9 - 21, 1928, (2 t.l. (carbon), ) (Box 5, Folder 24 - 25)
    - Wotton, Tom S. ms. notes on Beethoven's metronome, Brighton, [Dec. 1938 - Jan. 1939], (15p. t.ms., ) (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Wotton, Tom S. to: Jacques Barzun - receipt for payment for Wotton's Berlioz library, Brighton, [UK], 2 October, 1937, (1p. t.d.s., ) (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Wotton, Tom S. Some Misconceptions Concerning Berlioz, London, n.d., (8p. t.ms. ) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Subseries IV.2: Correspondence of Jacques Barzun relating to Hector Berlioz.
    Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence regarding Barzun's 1950 book Berlioz and the Romantic Century, the Berlioz Societies, performances, recordings, scholarship, archives and publications. Arranged chronologically.
    - Jacques Barzun, 1908 - 1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1932 - 1945 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jan. - Aug. 1949 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Jacques Barzun, Sep. - Dec. 1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jan. - Mar. 1950 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Barzun, Apr. - Jun. 1950 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jul. - Sep. 1950 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Jacques Barzun, Oct. - Dec. 1950 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jan. - May 1951 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jun. - Dec. 1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jan. - Jun. 1952 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jul. - Dec. 1952 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jan. - Mar. 1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Jacques Barzun, Apr. - Jun. 1953 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jul. - Dec. 1953 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Jacques Barzun, Jan. - Mar. 1954 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Barzun, Apr. - Sep. 1954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Jacques Barzun, Oct. - Dec. 1954 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1963 - 1964 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1965 - 1966 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1970 - 1971 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1973 - 1977 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1978 - 1980 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1981 - 1986 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Jacques Barzun, 1990 - 1992 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Series V: Berlioz Societies Records
  Correspondence, drafts, minutes of meetings, and printed materials relating to operations of Berlioz Societies in France, UK and US
  - Subseries V.1: France
    - Societe Nationale de la Fondation Berlioz - Correspondence and drafts, Paris, Grenoble, 1908 - 1917 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Societe Nationale de la Fondation Berlioz - Printed Materials, Paris, Grenoble, 1908 - 1917 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Association des Amis De Berlioz- programs and announcements, La Cote-St-Andre (Isere), 1935 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Association Nationale Hector Berlioz -Correspondence and Printed Materials, La Cote-St-Andre (Isere), 1966-1982 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Association Nationale Hector Berlioz -Bulletins and Supplements, La Cote-St-Andre (Isere), 1966-1982 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Association Nationale Hector Berlioz -Inter-Bulletins, La Cote-St-Andre (Isere), 1966-1975 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Subseries V.2: USA
    Society founded in 1953, Exeter, NH. Jacques The material is a Gift of Mr. Gillespie, a Secretary-Treasurer of the society
    - Berlioz Society: correspondence, notes, minutes, announcements, 1954-1971 (Box 12, Folder 4 - 5)
    - Berlioz Society Bank statements, 1954-1956 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Berlioz Society Newsletter, 1954-1960 (Box 12, Folder 7 - 9)
  - Subseries V.3: England
    Society was founded in 1952. President - Jacques Barzun.
    - Barzun Correspondence, 1954 - 1986 (Box 13, Folder 1 - 2)
    - Berlioz Society Bulletins, 1952-1962 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Berlioz Society Bulletins, 1966 - 1973 (Box 13, Folder 4 - 6)
    - Berlioz Society Bulletins and Indices to 1953 - 1973 Bulletins, 1974 - 1977 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Barzun Notes and Drafts
  Series consists of handwritten and typed notes, notebooks, index cards, drafts of various works by Barzun, including spiral notebooks and proofs for Berlioz and Romantic Century
  - Berlioz Fragments by J. B. 1930-1955; 1930-1955 (Box 14, Folder 1 - 3)
  - Notes and drafts on various composers (Box 14, Folder 4 - 6)
  - Essay proposals on Berlioz, 1958-1980 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Fragments on Revisions I - IV of Berlioz and the Romantic Century (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Essays and Interviews on Berlioz (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Notes - Supplement to New Letters by Berlioz (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Notes including Index to Berlioz letters on Les Troyens (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Notes on new Berlioz edition - Collected Works (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Bluebooks with Miscellaneous notes on Musical History (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Notes and listings on donation to Columbia University (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Ninon Vallin (Soprano), 1939 - 1955 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Orchestration (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Notebook - Berlioz Life and Works, index (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Notebook - Berlioz Fragments, 1930-1955 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Notebook - 363 Berlioz letters (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Notebook - notes and footnotes for works on Berlioz (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Notebook - reference indices for works on Berlioz (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Notebook - Background material for Berlioz and the Romantic Century, in alphabetical order (Box 17, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Notebook - Quotes and Sources on Berlioz (Box 17, Folder 5 - 6)
  - Notebook - Berlioz and the Romantic Century (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Berlioz and the Romantic Century Vol. 1 typescript (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Berlioz and the Romantic Century, 2nd Ed. - Edited Typescript and notes (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Galley proofs (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Proofs (Box 18, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Index cards with miscellaneous notes, index of books and recordings relating to Berlioz, (3x5 Index Cards) (Box 19)
  - Index cards listing original manuscripts by Berlioz with publication and location information, in chronological order, 1819 - 1853, (3x5 Index Cards) (Box 20)
  - Index cards listing original manuscripts by Berlioz with publication and location information, in chronological order, 1854 - 1868 and undated, (3x5 Index Cards) (Box 21)
    [Box 21 also contains 2 Microfilms (See Microfilms series)]
- Series VII: Research Materials
  Series consists of reference photostats of Berlioz manuscripts, typescripts of articles, proofs of dissertations related to Berlioz, and other research materials accumulated by Barzun for his works on Berlioz and music history.
  - Articles on musical subjects (mostly Berlioz) by various authors, 1884 - 1990 (Box 37, Folder 1 - 8)
    [Typescripts and printed materials, arranged in loose chronological order]
  - Berlioz scores, ms and published: Requiem, Faust, Romeo and Juliet, Death of Ophelia, Childhood of Christ, Trojans, reviews. (Box 38, Folder 1 - 3)
  - Berlioz reference copies (photostats and photocopies) (Box 38, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Hector Berlioz, The Art of Music and Other Essays, translated and edited by Elizabeth Csicsery-Ronay, foreword by Barzun, 1993 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    [Proofs]
  - Edinburgh Bibliographical Society Bibliography of the works of Hector Berlioz by Cecil Hopkinson, 1950 - 1951 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - John B. Ahouse Universityof Texas, El Paso Berlioz, The Centenniary Years: Bibliography of Articles in the Periodical Literature, 1967-71 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Berlioz Centenary Events, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Berlioz Research Materials (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Berlioz and the Romantic Century - Reviews, articles, printed materials, 1950 - 1980 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, Committee on Musicology Conference on Music in contemporary American Civilization, 1951 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Dictionary of Parisian Music Publishers (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Exhibitions on Berlioz, 1953 - 1969 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Electronic Music, 1960 - 1974 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - History Reference Council Materials, 1926 - 1937 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Music Education (Box 40, Folder 4)
    [: Syllabi, Tests, guidelines, memoranda]
  - Other composers music (Box 40, Folder 5 - 6)
    [Alphabetical by composer]
  - Louise Farenc Biography by Bea Friedland, 1982 (Box 41, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Miscellaneous Research Materials: Flyers, ads, notes, event tickets, etc, arranged chronologically, 1900 - 1989 (Box 41, Folder 3 - 8)
  - Photostats of scores, (3 pgs. Oversized, flat) (Box 46, Folder 2)
- Series VIII: Printed Materials
  Barzun collected flyers, pamphlets, programs, ads, catalogs, conference information, music education information, articles, and clippings--anything that pertained to Berlioz in particular and music in general. He considers the gathered material a history of criticism and taste. The assortment spans the 20th century. No complete runs.
  - Subseries VIII.1: Programs
    - Sub-subseries VIII.1.1: Individual Institutions
      Programs for specific institutions arranged alphabetically by institution, chronologically within institution.
      - Association des Concerts Lamoreux, 1902 - 1913 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Boston Symphony Orchestra, 1940 - 1973 (Box 22, Folder 2 - 4)
      - Carnegie Hall, 1913 - 1986 (Box 22, Folder 5 - 6)
      - Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra, 1950 - 1972 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Cleveland Symphony Orchestra, 1958 - 1962 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - Columbia University, 1930 - 1969 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Association Artistique des Concerts Colonne Concerts Colonne, 1903 - 1914 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Lincoln Center Philharmonic Hall, 1950 - 1977 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - The Little Orchestra Society, 1951 - 1983 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - The Philharmonic-Symphony Society of New York, 1929 - 1986 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Town Hall, New York, 1930 - 1986 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - WABF Radio, New York, 1947 - 1949 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - US Federal Works Progress Administration WPA Federal Music Project of New York City, 1936 - 1940 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Sub-subseries VIII.1.2: Arranged Chronologically
      - 1879 - 1900 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - 1901 - 1910 (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - 1911 - 1916 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Programs for Berlioz Requiem, 1908 - 1977 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Sub-subseries VIII.1.3: Arranged alphabetically
      Programs for concerts, festivals and other events, by institution, date span 1917 - 1990
      - A - F (Box 24, Folder 3 - 5)
      - G - Z (Box 25, Folder 1 - 7)
  - Subseries VIII.2: Catalogs
    - Sub-subseries VIII.2.1: Individual Titles/ Sellers
      - The American Record Guide, 1945 - 66 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Barenreiter, 1960 - 1980 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - The First Edition Bookshop, 1938 - 1965 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Fletcher, Ifan Kyrle, 1950 - 1967 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Gottlieb, Ernest / Front, Theodore, n. d. - 1970 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Grammophone Shop Catalogs, 1931 - 1937 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Grammophone Shop Supplements, 1936 - 1939 (Box 26, Folder 7)
        [Supplements only, since 1937]
      - Grammophone Shop Supplements, 1939 - 1950 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Macnutt, Richard, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 2)
      - Rabson's Music Shop, [n.d. - 1940] (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Sub-subseries VIII.2.2: Arranged alphabetically
      Catalogs by institution, date span, approx. 1920 - 1990
      - A - G (Box 27, Folder 4 - 5)
      - H - Z (Box 28, Folder 1 - 7)
  - Subseries VIII.3: Periodicals
    First two folders arranged chronologically, the rest of the subseries arranged alphabetically.
    - 1884 - 1909 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - 19th Century Music, 1984 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - A - American Records Guide, 1938 - 1969 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - The American Writer, 1952 - 1954 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Author's League Bulletin, 1940 - Jun. 1949 (Box 29, Folder 5 - 9)
    - B - BM, 1954 - 1966 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - BMI, 1954 - 1971 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Bo - Bz, 1908 - 1912 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - C - D, 1949 - 1970 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - E - G, 1928 - 1969 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - High Fidelity, 1954 - 1956 (Box 30, Folder 6 - 7)
    - I - K, 1952 - 1971 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - K - L, 1940 - 1945 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Magazine of Art, 1944 - 1953 (Box 31, Folder 3 - 4)
    - Music, 1957 - 1969 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - The Musical Quarterly, 1946 - 1974 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - The Musical Times, 1952 - 1969 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - N, 1928 - 1974 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - O, 1953 - 1967 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - P, 1953 - 1969 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Q - Res, 1940 - 1972 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - The Review of Politics, 1948 - 1950 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Revista Hispanica Moderna, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Revue - S, 1909 - 1957 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Saturday Night, 1954 (Box 46, Folder 1)
      [Oversized, flat box]
    - T - U, 1948 - 1954 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - V, 1909 - 1964 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - W - Z, 1949 - 1971 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Subseries VIII.4: Clippings
    This subseries contains clippings from newspapers and magazines. It includes articles, reviews, performance and radio schedules. The first files are in loose chronological order followed by subject order.
    - Sub-subseries VIII.4.1: Arranged Chronologically
      - 1834 - 1954 (Box 34, Folder 1 - 8)
      - 1955 - 1988 (Box 35, Folder 1 - 4)
      - undated (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Sub-subseries VIII.4.2: Subject Files, 1900 - 1986
      - Book Reviews (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - Le Corsair (Box 35, Folder 7)
      - Music Education (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - Music Technology (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - Musicians (Box 36, Folder 1 - 2)
        [Alphabetically, by name]
      - Opera (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - Orchestrations (Box 36, Folder 4)
      - Record Reviews (Box 36, Folder 5)
      - Les Troyens (Box 36, Folder 6)
      - Writers and Writing (Box 36, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous Musical/Cultural Subjects (Box 36, Folder 8)
      - Material on Barzun's Books and lectures (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - Subseries VIII.5: Booklets
    - Inauguration of Victor Hugo monument, Jul. 7, 1914 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Harold Eisenberg, Occupational Disorders of the Violinist, 1936 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Glen Haydon: On the Meaning of Music, 1948 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Leon Kochnitzky, Adolphe Sax and His Saxophone, 1949 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Herbert F. Peyser, Robert Schumann: Tone-poet, Prophet and Critic, 1948 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Subseries VIII.6: Books
    - Eric Blom, Music in England, London: Pelican Books, 1947 (Box 42)
    - Adolphe Boschot, La Jeunesse D'Un Romantique, Paris, 1906 (Box 42)
    - Berlioz Fantastic Symphony; Edward T. Cone, ed., New York: W. W. Norton and Co., 1971 (Box 42)
    - John Crabbe, Hector Berlioz: Rational Romantic, London: Kahn and Averill, 1980 (Box 42)
    - Texts of Choral Works Of Johann Sebastian Bach in English Translation by Henry S. Drinker, Vol. 3 (Box 42)
    - Marie Haefliger Graves, Schiller and Wagner, Ann Arbor, 1938 (Ph. D. Dissertation) (Box 42)
    - Willi Kahl, Selbstbiographien Deutscher Musiker, Staufen-Verlag, 1948 (Box 42)
    - Huhg Milton Miller, An Outline-History of Music, New York: Barnes & Noble, 1947 (Box 42)
    - Katherine. K. Reeve, Berlioz; Poetics of the Orchestra, Yale University, 1978 (Ph. D. Dissertation) (Box 42)
    - Bruno Walter, Gustav Mahler, New York: Vienna House, 1973 (Box 42)
    - R. P. Winnington-Ingram, Mode in Ancient Greek Music, Cambridge: University Press, 1936 (Box 42)
  - Subseries VIII.7: Librettos
    - Librettos of operas by Mozart, Claude Debussy, Richard Wagner, Richard Strauss, Giuseppe Verdi, Giacomo Puccini, Pietro Mascagni, Ildebrando Pizzetti, Leo Delibes, Gustave Charpentier, A. Catalani, Deems Taylor, Gilbert and Sullivan. (Box 43)
  - Subseries VIII.8: Scores
    - Berlioz, Hector Published scores, [c. 1900], (Oversized, flat, ) (Box 46)
- Series IX: Audiovisual Materials
  - Subseries IX.1: Audiotapes
    - Jacques Barzun - Berlioz, Feb. 25, 1969, (1 reel (1200 ft) 1/4 inch magnetic tape, Hector Berlioz and Friends Parts 1 and 2, Jaques Barzun/Berlioz 25 February 1969, ) (Box 44)